What do you guys think?
ماذا تعتقدون؟
For those who watched Sir Ken's memorable TED Talk,
لهؤلاء ممن شاهدوا حديث TED
I am a typical example of what he describes
أنا مثال حي لما وصف
as "the body as a form of transport for the head,"
كما يقال" الجسد كوسيلة للوصول الى الرأس"
a university professor.
بروفيسور جامعي
You might think it was not fair
قد تعتقدون انه من غير المنصف
that I've been lined up to speak after these first two talks
أني أتحدث بعد
to speak about science.
للتحدث عن العلوم
I can't move my body to the beat,
لا استطيع تحريك جسدي من التوتر
and after a scientist who became a philosopher,
بعد عالم أصبح فيلسوفا
I have to talk about hard science.
عليّ أن اتحدث عن علم صعب
It could be a very dry subject.
قد يكون الموضوع جافا كثيرا
Yet, I feel honored.
و مع ذلك اشعر بالشرف.
Never in my career,
لم تتح لي أبدا في حياتي المهنية
and it's been a long career,
و التي كانت طويلة
have I had the opportunity to start a talk
الفرصة بأن أبدأ حديثا
feeling so inspired, like this one.
مليئ بالالهام كهذه المرة
Usually, talking about science
عادة الحديث عن العلم
is like exercising in a dry place.
هو كالتمرين في مكان شديد الحرارة
However, I've had the pleasure
و على الرغم من ذلك فقد حظيت بالمتعة
of being invited to come here to talk about water.
لدعوتي هنا للتكلم عن المياه
The words "water" and "dry" do not match, right?
الكلمتان "مياه" و"جاف" لا تتوافقان، اليس كذلك؟
It is even better to talk about water in the Amazon,
و الأفضل أيضا الحديث
which is the splendid cradle of life. Fresh life.
منشأ الحياة الرائعة، الحياة المنعشة
So this is what inspired me.
اذا هذا ما ألهمني.
That's why I'm here, although I'm carrying
لهذا السبب أنا هنا مع العلم
my head over here.
أشعر بصعوبة الموضوع
I am trying, or will try to convey this inspiration.
انا أحاول، او سأحاول توصيل هذا الالهام
I hope this story will inspire you and that you'll spread the word.
أتمنى ان تلهمكم هذه القصة و تنشروها بعدي.
We know that there is controversy.
نحن نعلم أن هناك جدل
The Amazon is the "lung of the world,"
بأن الامازون هو "رئة العالم,"
because of its massive power to have vital gases exchanged
لقدرته الهائلة لتبديل الغازات الحيوية
between the forest and the atmosphere.
بين الغابة و الغلاف الجوي.
We also hear about the storehouse of biodiversity.
سمعنا أيضا عن مستودع التنوع البيولوجي
While many believe it,
في حين أن ما يعتقده الكثير
few know it.
يعرفه القليل فقط
If you go out there, in this marsh,
لو ذهبت الى هناك، الى هذا المستنقع،
you'll be amazed at the --
ستذهل حين
You can barely see the animals.
من النادر أن تروا الحيوانات
The Indians say, "The forest has more eyes than leaves."
يقول الهنود، «للغابة عيون اكثر من اوراق الشجر»
That is true, and I will try to show you something.
هذا صحيح، و سأحاول ان أريكم شيئا.
But today, I'm going to use a different approach,
ولكن اليوم، سأستخدم أسلوبا مخلتف،
one that is inspired by these two initiatives here,
أسلوب مستوحي من هاتين المبادرتين هنا،
a harmonic one and a philosophical one.
إحداهما توافقية والثانية فلسفية
I'll try to use an approach that's slightly materialistic,
سأحاول استخدام أسلوب مادي قليلا،
but it also attempts to convey that, in nature, there is
و لكن أحاول أيضا نقل الفكرة انه هناك في الطبيعة
extraordinary philosophy and harmony.
انسجام و فلسفة غير عادية
There'll be no music in my presentation,
لن يكون هناك موسيقى أثناء عرضي
but I hope you'll all notice the music of the reality I'm going to show you.
لكن أتمنى ان تلاحظوا جميعكم موسيقى الواقع الذي سأعرضه
I'm going to talk about physiology — not about lungs,
سأتكلم عن الفيسولوجيا، لا عن الرئة،
but other analogies with human physiology,
ولكن تشبيهات أخرى لفسيولوجيا الانسان،
especially the heart.
خاصة القلب
We'll start
سنبدأ
by thinking that water is like blood.
عن طريق التفكير بأن المياه كالدم
The circulation in our body distributes fresh blood,
الدورة الدموية توزع الدم المتجدد،
which feeds, nurtures and supports us,
الذي يطعمنا و يغذينا و يدعمنا،
and brings the used blood back to be renewed.
و تسحب الدم المستعمل لأعادة تجديده،
In the Amazon, things happen similarly.
في الامازون، الوضع متشابه
We'll start by talking about the power of all these processes.
سنبدأ بالحديث عن قوة كل هذه العمليات
This is an image
هذه صورة
of rain in motion.
لحركة المطر
What you see there is the years passing in seconds.
ما ترونها هنا هي السنين تمر في ثواني
Rains all over the world. What do you see?
مطر في جميع انحاء العالم، ماذا ترون؟
The equatorial region, in general,
المنطقة الاستوائية، بشكل عام،
and the Amazon specifically,
و خاصة الأمازون،
is extremely important for the world's climate.
هامة جدا لمناخ العالم
It's a powerful engine.
إنها محرك قوي
There is a frantic evaporation taking place here.
توجد عملية تبخير محمومة تجري هنا
If we take a look at this other image,
إن ألقينا النظر على هذه الصورة الأخرى،
which shows the water vapor flow,
التي تبين تدفق البخار المائي،
you have dry air in black, moist air in gray,
الهواء الجاف بالاسود، و الهواء الرطب بالرمادي،
and clouds in white.
و الغيوم بالأبيض
What you see there is an extraordinary resurgence in the Amazon.
ما ترونه هناك هي حركة مدهشة في الامازون
What phenomenon -- if it's not a desert,
ما هي الظاهرة ؟ ، اذا لم تكن الصحراء !
what phenomenon makes water gush from the ground into the atmosphere
ما هي الظاهرة التي تجعل الماء يتدفق من الارض الى المحيط الجوي ؟
with such power that it can be seen from space?
بهذه القوة التي ممكن ان ترى من الفضاء؟
What phenomenon is this?
اي ظاهرة هذه؟
It could be a geyser.
قد تكون عيونا ساخنة
A geyser is underground water heated by magma,
و العيون الساخنة هي مياه تحت الارض تسخن بواسطه الصهارة،
exploding into the atmosphere
وتتفجر في المحيط الجوي
and transferring this water into the atmosphere.
وتنقل هذه المياه الى الغلاف الجوي
There are no geysers in the Amazon, unless I am wrong.
لا توجد عيون ساخنة في الامازون، اذا لم اكن مخطئا.
I don't know of any.
لا اعلم وجود اي منها
But we have something that plays the same role,
و لكن عندنا شيء يلعب نفس الدور
with much more elegance though:
و بأناقة أكثر بكثير:
the trees, our good old friends
انها الأشجار، أصدقاؤنا القربى
that, like geysers,
والتي، مثل العيون الساخنة،
can transfer an enormous amount of water from the ground into the atmosphere.
تستطيع نقل كمية هائلة من الماء من الارض الى الغلاف الجوي
There are 600 billion trees in the Amazon forest, 600 billion geysers.
هناك اكثر من 600 مليار شجرة في الامازون، 600 مليار من العيون الساخنة
That is done with an extraordinary sophistication.
هذا يحدث بتعقيدات هائلة
They don't need the heat of magma.
لا يحتاجون الى حرارة الصهارة.
They use sunlight to do this process.
يستخدمون الشمس للقيام بهذا الدور,
So, in a typical sunny day in the Amazon,
ففي اليوم المشمس في الامازون,
a big tree manages to transfer 1,000 liters of water
تستطيع الشجرة العملاقة ان تنقل 1,000 لتر من المياة
through its transpiration --
عن طريق النتح
1,000 liters.
1,000 لتر.
If we take all the Amazon,
لو اخذنا كل الأمازون
which is a very large area,
و هي مساحة كبيرة جدا
and add it up to all that water that is released by transpiration,
و جمعنا كل الماء المنتج من النتح
which is the sweat of the forest,
و الذي هو بالاحرى تعرق الغابة
we'll get to an incredible number:
سنحصل على رقم مذهل:
20 billion metric tons of water.
20 مليار طن مكعب من المياة.
In one day.
في يوم واحد
Do you know how much that is?
هل تتخيلون كم يبلغ كل هذا؟
The Amazon River, the largest river on Earth,
نهر الامازون ,الاكبر في العالم
one fifth of all the fresh water
خمس المياة العذبة في العالم
dumps 17 billion metric tons of water a day in the Atlantic Ocean.
تصب 17 مليار طن متر مكعب من المياه يوميا في المحيط الأطلسي.
This river of vapor
هذا النهر المتبخر
is greater than the Amazon River.
الى المحيط الجوي, أكبر من نهر الامازون.
Just to give you an idea.
هو أكبر من نهر الأمازون
the kind you could plug into a power socket, an electric one,
فقط للتوضيح
and put those 20 billion metric tons of water in it,
اذا أخذنا وعاء عملاق
how much power would you need to have this water evaporated?
كم مقدار الطاقة ستحتاج لتبخير تلك المياة؟
Any idea? A really big kettle.
أي تصور؟ براد كبير حقا
A gigantic kettle, right?
براد عملاق,صحيح؟
50 thousand Itaipus.
50 الف ايتابو
Itaipu is still the largest hydroelectric plant in the world.
ايتابو مازال هو اكبر مولد للطاقة الطاقة الكهرومائية في العالم
and Brazil is very proud of it
لأنه ينتج أكثر من 30 بالمئه من الطاقة
And the Amazon is here, doing this for free.
و هنا الامازون, يفعل هذا بدون مقابل.
we are going to talk about what I call the paradox of chance,
ما أسميه " مفارقة الفرصة"
which is curious.
الذي يبدو مثير للاهتمام.
If you look at the world map --
لو نظرت الى خريطة العالم
and from São Paulo to the Andes.
و من سان باولو الى جبال الانديز
Why isn't it? That's why I call it the paradox of chance.
لماذا ليست كذلك؟ هذا ما اسميه "مفارقة الفرصة"
If we could use the analogy
لو نأخذ مثال توزيع الدم في اجسامنا
we see that rivers are veins,
نرى الانهار كأنها أوردة
they drain the landscape, they drain the tissue of nature.
تقوم بتفريغ سطوح الطبيعة وبتفريغ انسجة الطبيعة
Where are the arteries?
اذن أين الشرايين؟
Any guess?
هل من تخمين؟
What takes --
ما الذي يأخذ ...
How does water get to irrigate the tissues of nature
كيف يروي الماء انسجة الطبيعة؟
There is a new type of river,
هذا النوع الجديد من الأنهار
which originates in the blue sea,
الذي يبدأ في البحر الازرق
which flows through the green ocean --
ويمر خلال المحيط الاخضر
it not only flows, but it is also pumped by the green ocean --
ليس فقط يمر بالمحيط الاخضر لكن ايضا يضخه
and then it falls on our land.
وبعد ذلك يسقط في أرضنا
All our economy, that quadrangle,
كل اقتصادنا , تلك المساحة
70 percent of South America's GDP comes from that area.
٧٠٪ من اقتصاد أمريكا الجنوبية يأتي من تلك المنطقة
It depends on this river.
هي تعتمد على هذا النهر
This river flows invisibly above us.
النهر يسير بطريقة غير مرئية فوقنا
We are floating here on this floating hotel,
نحن نطفو هنا على هذا الفندق العائم
on one of the largest rivers on Earth, the Negro River.
على واحد من أكبر الأنهار في الأرض ؛ نهر نيجرو
It's a bit dry and rough, but we are floating here,
هو جاف قليلا وقاسي لكننا نطفو هنا
and there is this invisible river running above us.
وهناك هذا النهر غير المرئي يجري فوقنا
This river has a pulse.
هذا النهر له نبض
Here it is, pulsing.
هذا هو ، ينبض
That's why we also talk about the heart.
ولهذا السبب نحن نتحدث عن القلب أيضا
You can see the different seasons there.
نستطيع أن نرى الفصول المختلفة هناك
There's the rainy season. In the Amazon, we used to have two seasons,
في الأمازون
the humid season and the even more humid season.
الموسم الرطب ، والموسم الأكثر رطوبة
Now we have a dry season.
الآن لدينا موسم جاف
You can see the river covering that region
تستطيع رؤية النهر يغطي المنطقة
which, otherwise, would be a desert. And it is not.
ولولا ذلك لكانت صحراء ، ولكنه ليس كذلك
We, scientists -- You see that I'm struggling here
نحن العلماء ، تستطيعون رؤية أني أعاني هنا
to move my head from one side to the other.
في تحريك رأسي من جهة لأخرى
Scientists study how it works, why, etc.
العلماء يدرسون كيف تعمل ولماذا، الخ...
and these studies are generating a series of discoveries,
وهذه الدراسات تولد سلسلة من الاكتشافات
which are absolutely fabulous,
والذي هو رائع حقا
to raise our awareness of the wealth,
أن يزيد الوعي لدينا عن ثروة
the complexity, and the wonder that we have,
التعقيد والروعة التي نملكها
the symphony we have in this process.
السيمفونية التي نملكها في هذه العملية
One of them is: How is rain formed?
واحدة منها هي كيف تتكون هذه الأمطار؟
Above the Amazon, there is clean air,
فوق الأمازون هناك هواء نظيف
as there is clean air above the ocean.
فوق البحر الأزرق هواء نظيف يكون بعض السحب
The blue sea has clean air above it and forms pretty few clouds;
لايوجد هناك مطر تقريبا
there's almost no rain there.
البحر الأخضر لديه نفس الهواء النظيف لكنه يكون الكثير من الأمطار
What is happening here that is different?
الغابة تبعث روائح
The forest emits smells,
وهذه الروائح هي نوى التكييف
and these smells are condensation nuclei,
التي تكون قطرات في الغلاف الجوي
which form drops in the atmosphere.
وبعد ذلك تتكون السحب والمطر المتدفق
Then, clouds are formed and there is torrential rain.
رذاذ جنة عدن
The sprinkler of the Garden of Eden.
هذه العلاقة بين كائن حي ( الغابة)
This relation between a living thing, which is the forest,
وكائن غير حي ( الغلاف الجوي)
and a nonliving thing, which is the atmosphere,
هي مبتكرة في الأمازون
is ingenious in the Amazon,
لأن الغابة تكون المطر وتعطي الماء والبذور
because the forest provides water and seeds,
والغلاف الجوي يكون المطر والماء من جديد
and the atmosphere forms the rain and gives water back,
مما يضمن بقاء الغابة
guaranteeing the forest's survival.
هناك غابات أخرى أيضا
There are other factors as well.
تكلمنا قليلا عن القلب
We've talked a little about the heart,
لنتكلم الآن عن وظيفة أخرى هي الكبد!
and let's now talk about another function: the liver!
عندما تجتمع الرطوبة العالية و الهواء الرطب والاشعاع
which I call exogenous vitamin C, generous vitamin C in the form of gas,
النباتات تفرز مضادات أكسدة..تتفاعل مع التلوث
the plants release antioxidants
تستطيعون الشعور بالراحة
which react with pollutants.
انكم تتنفسون أنقى هواء على الأرض هنا في الأمازون
You can rest assured
لأن النباتات تعتني بهذه الصفات أيضا
because the plants take care of this characteristic as well.
تستطبع الشعور بالراحة
This benefits the very way plants work,
أنك تتنفس أنقى هواء
which is another ingenious cycle.
هنا في الأمازون
Speaking of fractals,
نستطيع انشاء مقارنات أخرى.
and their relation with the way we work,
.مثل الجزء الأعلى من رئتنا
we can establish other comparisons.
الهواء في الأمازون تتم تنقيته من الغبار الزائد
As in the upper airways of our lungs,
الغبار في الهواء الذي نتنفسه تتم تنقيته في مجالاتنا الهوائية
The dust in the air that we breathe is cleaned by our airways.
من التأثير على سقوط المطر
This keeps the excess of dust from affecting the rainfall.
عندما يكون هناك حريق في الأمازون
When there are fires in the Amazon,
الدخان يوقف المطر
the smoke stops the rain, it stops raining,
الغابة تجف وتتمسك بالنيران
the forest dries up and catches fire.
هناك تشبيه آخر، كما في الأوردة والشرايين
There is another fractal analogy.
ماء المطر عبارة عن تغذية راجعة
Like in the veins and arteries,
هو يرجع للغلاف الجوي
the rain water is a feedback.
كما في افرازات الغدد والهرمونات
It returns to the atmosphere.
هناك تلك الغازات التي أخبرتكم عنها سابقا
Like endocrinal glands and hormones,
التي يتم تكوينها واطلاقها في الغلاف الجوي كالهرمونات
there are those gases which I told you about before,
والتي تسهم في تكوين المطر
that are formed and released into the atmosphere, like hormones,
كالكبد والكلى كما ذكرت سابقا ، تنظف الهواء
which help in the formation of rain.
تضخ المياه من الخارج من البحر
Like the liver and the kidneys, as I've said, cleaning the air.
لداخل الغابة
And, finally, like the heart:
نطلق عليها الضخ الرطب الحيوي
pumping water from outside, from the sea,
نظرية جديدة يتم طرحها بطريقة بسيطة جدا
into the forest.
اذا كان هناك صحراء في القارة
We call it the biotic moisture pump,
مع بحر مجاور
a new theory that is explained in a very simple way.
التبخر يكون أعظم في البحر
If there is a desert in the continent
ويمتص الهواء فوق الصحراء
with a nearby sea,
الصحراء محاصرة في هذا الوضع وستكون دوما جافة
evaporation's greater on the sea,
اذا كان هناك وضع آخر ، كالغابة مثلا
If you have the opposite situation, a forest,
ويتم تصدير الرطوبة
the evaporation, as we showed, is much greater, because of the trees,
صور القمر الصناعي التي تم أخذها قبل شهر
and this relation is reversed.
في ماناواس في الأسفل هنا
The air above the sea is sucked into the continent
انه ليس نهر معتاد صغير يصب في القناة
and humidity is imported.
انه نهر عظيم يعبر عبر أمريكا الجنوبية
This satellite image was taken one month ago —
من بين أشياء أخرى
that's Manaus down there, we're down there —
الصور تظهر هذه الطرق
and it shows this process.
كل الأعاصير التي تم تسجيلها
It's not a common little river that flows into a canal.
هذا نهر عظيم يعبر أمريكا الجنوبية
It's a mighty river that irrigates South America,
وهذه ليست مصادفة
among other things.
هذا المضخ الذي يمتص الرطوبة نحو القارة
This image shows those paths,
الصورة ترينا هذه الطرق
all the hurricanes that have been recorded.
كل الأاعاصير التي تم تسجيلها
You can see that, in the red square, there hardly are any hurricanes.
تستطيعون رؤية أنه في الجزء الأحمر لاتوجد أية آعاصير
That is no accident.
وهذا ليس بصدفة
This pump that sucks the moisture into the continent
هذ المضخات تعمل على امتصاص الرطوبة وتوجيهها نحو القارة
also speeds up the air above the sea,
كما تسرع من حركة الهواء فوق البحر
and this prevents hurricane formations.
مما يمنع من تكون الأعاصير
To close this part and sum up,
لانهاء وتلخيص هذا الجزء
I'd like to talk about something a little different.
أود التحدث عن شئ مختلف
I have several colleagues
لدي زملاء عديدون
who worked in the development of these theories.
الذين عملوا على تطوير هذه النظريات
They think, and so do I,
هم يعتقدون وأنا أيضا
that we can save planet Earth.
أنه بامكاننا انقاذ كوكب الأرض
I'm not talking only about the Amazon.
أنا لا أتحدث عن الأمازون
The Amazon teaches us a lesson
الأمازون يعلمنا درسا
on how pristine nature works.
عن دقة الطبيعة في العمل
We didn't understand these processes before
لم نفهم هذه العمليات قبلا
because the rest of the world is messed up.
لأن باقي العالم تعمه الفوضى
We could understand it here, though.
بامكاننا فهمه هنا
These colleagues propose that, yes, we can
هؤلاء الزملاء يقترحون بأنه
save other areas,
بامكاننا انقاذ مناطق أخرى
including deserts.
بما فيها الصحاري
If we could establish forests in those other areas,
اذا أنشأنا غابات في مناطق أخرى
we can reverse climate change,
بامكاننا عكس التقلبات المناخية
including global warming.
بما في ذلك التوازن الحراري
I have a dear colleague in India,
أود أن أخبركم قصة قصيرة
whose name is Suprabha Seshan, and she has a motto.
لدي زميلة عزيزة في الهند
Her motto is, "Gardening back the biosphere,"
اعادة زراعة الأرض
She does a wonderful job rebuilding ecosystems.
نحتاج للقيام بذلك
We need to do this.
بعد انهاء هذا الحديث
Having closed this quick introduction,
نستطيع رؤية الواقع
we see the reality that we have out here,
في أحدى المرات
which is drought, this climate change,
حضرت خطابا لممثل الشعب اليانومامي
things that we already knew.
كان يقول: "ألا يعلم الرجل الأبيض؟
I'd like to tell you a short story.
أنه اذا دمر الغابة سيتوقف المطر؟
Once, about four years ago,
لقد قمت بدراسة هذا لمدة عشرين عاما بواسطة كومبيوتر متقدم
I attended a declamation, of a text by Davi Kopenawa,
المئات والآلاف من العلماء يدرسون هذا
a wise representative of the Yanomami people,
لنتوصل للنتيجة هذه التي يعرفها مسبقا!؟
and it went more or less like this:
نقطة مهمة ان هذا الشعب لم تتدمر غابتهم قبلا
"Doesn't the white man know
فكيف توصلو لأن تدمير الغابات ممكن أن يوقف الأمطار ؟
that, if he destroys the forest, there will be no more rain?
لقد أدهشني كثيرا !
And that, if there's no more rain,
كيف من الممكن أن يعرف هذا ؟
I heard that, and my eyes welled up
"دافي كيف تعرف لو أن الغابة تدمرت فسيتوقف المطر؟"
and I went, "Oh, my!
أجاب:" روح الغابة أجابتنا"
I've been studying this for 20 years, with a super computer,
تغيرت اللعبة بالنسبة لي
dozens, thousands of scientists,
تغييرا جذريا
and we are starting to get to this conclusion, which he already knows!"
قلت: " يا الهي !
A critical point is the Yanomami have never deforested.
لماذا أقوم بهذه الدراسات والعلوم؟
How could they know the rain would end?
لأتوصل لنتيجة يعرفها مسبقا؟
This bugged me and I was befuddled.
بعد ذلك حدث لي شئ مهم
How could he know that?
ألا وهو
Some months later, I met him at another event and said,
الحق هو ما تراه العين
"Davi, how did you know that if the forest was destroyed, there'd be no more rain?"
مايبعد عن عينك يبعد عن عقلك
He replied: "The spirit of the forest told us."
هذه حاجة تفوه بها المتحدث السابق
For me, this was a game changer,
أعني نحن المجتمع الغربي
a radical change.
الذين أصبحنا متحضرين ومتطورين
I said, "Gosh!
نحتاج لنرى
Why am I doing all this science
اذا لم نرى فلن نسجل المعلومات
to get to a conclusion that he already knows?"
نحن نعيش في جهل
Then, something absolutely critical hit me,
لذلك أقترح التالي
which is,
من المؤكد أن عالم الفضاء لن تعجبه الفكرة
seeing is believing.
لنقلب التلسكوب هابل رأسا على عقب
Out of sight, out of mind.
ماهو بعيد عن ناظريك بعيد عن عقلك!
This is a need the previous speaker pointed out:
بدلا أن يتوجه نحو الأكوان البعيدة
We need to see things --
الكون رائع
I mean, we, Western society,
ولكننا نعيش حقيقة
which is becoming global, civilized --
أننا نعيش في عوالم مجهولة
we need to see.
نحن جاهلون بها
If we don't see, we don't register the information.
ونتخبط فيها
We live in ignorance.
هي تحمينا وتؤوينا
So, I propose the following --
تحدث لأي عالم فيزياء فلكية
of course, the astronomer wouldn't like the idea --
سيخبرك أن الأرض لا احصائية
but let's turn the Hubble telescope upside down.
الاستقرار والراحة التي نعيشها بالرغم من عدم استقرار نهر النيجرو
And let's make it look down here,
كل الحرارة والبرودة
rather than to the far reaches of the universe.
لا يوجد مثيل لها في الكون الذي نعرفه
The universe is wonderful,
لذا لندير هابل نحونا
but we have a practical reality,
ولننظر نحو الأرض
which is we live in an unknown cosmos,
ولنبدأ بالأمازون!
and we're ignorant about it.
لنستكشف هذه العوالم
We're trampling on this wonderful cosmos
ونستكشف الواقع الذي نعيشه يوميا
that shelters us and houses us.
ولننظر اليه بتمعن بما أننا نحتاج لذلك
Talk to any astrophysicist.
دافي كابيناوي لايحتاج لذلك
The Earth is a statistical improbability.
هو لديه شئ نفتقده
The stability and comfort that we enjoy, despite the droughts of the Negro River,
لقد تم تعليمي من قبل التلفاز
and all the heat and cold and typhoons, etc.,
تاريخ مسجل من قبل الأسلاف
there is nothing like it in the universe, that we know of.
تقييم للأشياء التي لم أعرفها ولم أراها
Then, let's turn Hubble in our direction,
لنأخذ منظار هابل
and let's look at the Earth.
لنغوص في الأرض
Let's start with the Amazon!
ولننظر للأمازون
Let's dive,
و لننظر للغابة
let's reach out the reality we live in every day,
حتى مع وجود هابل
and look carefully at it, since that's what we need.
يعد منظارا محدودا كعين طائر أاليس كذلك!
Davi Kopenawa doesn't need this.
حتى عندما يحدث ذلك نحن نرى شيئا لانعرفه
He has something already that I think I missed.
حتى عندما يحدث ذلك
I was educated by television.
نحن نرى شيئا لانعرفه
I think that I missed this,
الاسبان يطلقون عليه " الجحيم الأخضر"
an ancestral record,
عندما تذهب الى الأدغال وتضيع
a valuation of what I don't know, what I haven't seen.
من الممكن أن يكون تقييما لما لم أره ولم أعرفه
He is not a doubting Thomas.
هو ليس بمتشكك
He believes, with veneration and reverence,
سيأخذنا المنظار
in what his ancestors and the spirits taught him.
لأعماق الأمازون
We can't do it, so let's look into the forest.
لنستكشف هذه العوالم
Even with Hubble up there --
البعيدة عن ناظرنا
this is a bird's-eye view, right?
نحن نرى هنا شيئا لا نعرفه
Even when this happens,
الاسبان يطلقون عليه الجحيم الأخضر
we also see something that we don't know.
فلنذهب هنا الى الأدغال ونضيع
The Spanish called it the green inferno.
ولنقل حين تتجه غربا
If you go out there into the bushes and get lost,
هي على بعد ٩٠٠ كلم من كولومبيا
and, let's say, if you head west,
و١٠٠٠ كلم أخرى في مكان آخر
it's 900 kilometers to Colombia,
حتى نكتشف لماذا يطلقون عليها الجحيم الأخضر
and another 1,000 to somewhere else.
ولكن اذهب وانظر ماذا يوجد هناك
So, you can figure out why they called it the green inferno.
هو سجاد حي
But go and look at what is in there.
كل لون تراه
It is a live carpet.
هو عبارة عن فصيلة من الأشجار
Each color you see is a tree species.
كل شجرة ، كل قمة شجرة
Each tree, each tree top,
فيها 10 آلاف فصيلة من الحشرات
has up to 10,000 species of insects in it,
غير ملايين الفصائل الأخرى من الفطريات والبكتريا الخ
let alone the millions of species of fungi, bacteria, etc.
كل نوع هو عالم غريب عنا
All invisible.
أغرب من ملايين المجرات
All of it is an even stranger cosmos to us
البعيدة جدا عنا
than the galaxies billions of light years away from the Earth,
بميلايين السنين الضوئية عن كوكب الأرض
which Hubble brings to our newspapers everyday.
والتي يحضر لنا منظار هابل يوميا صورها
I'm going to end my talk here --
لدي بعض الثواني المتبقية
I have a few seconds left --
سوف أنهي حديثي
by showing you this wonderful being.
بالحديث عن هذا الكائن الرائع
When we see the morpho butterfly in the forest,
عندما نرى فراشة المورفو في الغابة
we feel like someone's left open the door to heaven,
نشعر بأن أحدا فتح لنا باب الجنة
However, I cannot finish
ولكن لاأستطيع أن أنتهي
without showing you a tech side.
دون أن أذكر لكم الجانب التقني
We are tech-arrogant.
نحن جاهلون به
We deprive nature of its technology.
نحن نحرم الطبيعة من تقنيتها
A robotic hand is technological,
يد الروبوت تقنية
mine is biological,
بينما يدي حيوية
and we don't think about it anymore.
ونحن لم نعد نفكر بذلك
Let's then look at the morpho butterfly,
لننظر الى فراشة المورفو
an example of an invisible technological competence of life,
مثال على الجانب التقني الابداعي في الحياة
which is at the very heart of our possibility of surviving on this planet,
والذي هو مرتبط بامكانية بقاءنا على هذا الكوكب
and let's zoom in on it. Again, Hubble is there.
ولننظر الى هذه الصورة
Let's get into the butterfly's wings.
حاول العلماء تفسير لم لونها أزرق
Scholars have tried to explain: Why is it blue?
لنقرب منها أكثر
Let's zoom in on it.
مايوجد هنا هو هندسة غير مرئية
What you see is that the architecture of the invisible humiliates
أعظم هندسة في العالم
the best architects in the world.
كل هذا على مقياس صغير جدا
All of this on a tiny scale.
بجانب جمالها ووظيفتها هناك جانب آخر
Besides its beauty and functioning, there is another side to it.
كل ماهو موجود في هذه التركيبات العظيمة له وظيفة
In nature,
في الطبيعة
This function of the morpho butterfly — it is not blue;
جناح هذه الفراشة
it does not have blue pigments.
لايوجد به صبغ أورق
It has photonic crystals on its surface, according to people who studied it,
لديها فوتونات بلورية
which are extremely sophisticated crystals.
هيتاتشي قامت بصنع شاشة
Our technology had nothing like that at the time.
بإستخدام هذه التقنية
Hitachi has now made a monitor
الموجودة في الفراشة والتي هي عبارة عن
that uses this technology,
الياف بصرية على سطحه للنقل
and it is used in optical fibers to transmit --
تحدث عن هذا التقليد الأحيائى بينياس عدة مرات
Janine Benyus, who's been here several times, talks about it: biomimetics.
وقتي انتهى
of this competence of biodiversity,
التي تقوم بانتاج كل هذه الخدمات لنا
producing all these wonderful services:
والتي هي متمثلة في
the living cell.
الخلية الحية
It is a structure with a few microns, which is an internal wonder.
" عجيبة داخلية"
There are TED Talks about it. I won't talk much longer,
هناك حديث في تيد عنه لن أتحدث أكثر
but each person in this room, including myself,
كل شخص في هذه الغرفة بمن فيهم أنا
has 100 trillion of these micromachines in their body,
لديه مئة تريليون من الآلات الدقيقة في جسده
so that we can enjoy well-being.
تخيلوا مايوجد هناك في غابات الآمازون
Imagine what is out there in the Amazon forest:
تخيلو مايوجد هناك في غابات الآمازون
100 trillion. This is greater than the number of stars in the sky.
مئة تريليون! هذا أكبر من عدد نجوم السماء
And we are not aware of it.
ونحن غير مدركون ذلك
Thank you so much. (Applause)
شكرا جزيلا لكم